<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The churches plea for the divine presence to prosper humane force in a sermon preached June 5, 1689, being the day appointed for a general fast and to implore the blessing of almighty God upon Their Majesties arms / by T. Cruso.</title>
            <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11283304</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11283304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47281</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47281)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1459:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The churches plea for the divine presence to prosper humane force in a sermon preached June 5, 1689, being the day appointed for a general fast and to implore the blessing of almighty God upon Their Majesties arms / by T. Cruso.</title>
                  <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>War --  Religious aspects --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47281:1"/>
            <p>THE Churches Plea FOR THE <hi>Divine Preſence</hi> To Proſper HUMANE FORCE.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON Preached, <hi>June</hi> 5. 1689. Being the Day appointed for a General Faſt, and to Implore the Bleſſing of Almighty God upon <hi>Their Majeſties Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. CR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SO.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>DEUTER. 33.7.</bibl>
               <p>Hear, Lord, the voice of Judah, and bring him unto his people; let his hands be ſufficient for him, and be thou an Help to him from his Enemies.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.R.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Salusbury,</hi> at the Riſing <hi>Sun,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47281:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47281:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IF ever it were Seaſonable, ſince we were a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to <hi>ſanctify a Faſt, and call a ſolemn Aſſembly,</hi> we muſt acknowledge it to be Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſo, when the <hi>Wiſedom</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> of our Governours lately put us upon that work. <hi>What King</hi> (ſayes our Saviour) <hi>going to make War againſt another, ſitteth not down firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 14.31.</note> 
               <hi>and conſulteth whether he be able to meet him that cometh againſt him?</hi> But the conſultation in ſuch caſes may be either <hi>Prudential,</hi> or <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> and when the <hi>meer Politician</hi> upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſome viſible advantages on his own ſide, is ready to cry out (with thoſe forward <hi>Sons of Zebedee</hi>) <hi>We are able,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 20.22.</note> the <hi>ſerious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:47281:3"/>ſtops a while, and looks higher than any thing here below, that the <hi>ſtrong God</hi> may be united with him, before he adventures to contend with the <hi>weakeſt Adverſary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far the <hi>external ſtrictneſs</hi> in moſt places upon this occaſion, was accompanied with <hi>internal Zeal,</hi> the ſearcher of hearts only can determine; whether there was an <hi>awe</hi> upon mens <hi>ſpirits,</hi> ſuitable to the <hi>reverence</hi> of their <hi>Behaviour,</hi> is not known to us;<note place="margin">Rom. 14.6.</note> But if they who <hi>regarded that day, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded it to the Lord,</hi> (and not as an <hi>Humane ordinance</hi> impoſed againſt their wills) we need not doubt of an happy and proſperous event. A <hi>Faſt which God hath choſen,</hi> (that is, when our obſervation is according to his Inſtitution) is a faſt which God will <hi>bleſſe:</hi> a day of the <hi>aflicting of ſouls,</hi> uſhers in <hi>a day of ſalvation</hi> to <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes:</hi> though on the other hand, all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances <hi>of Repentance</hi> (if they are no more than <hi>appearances</hi>) make our <hi>ſin</hi> the <hi>greater,</hi> and conſequently may make our <hi>deſtruction</hi> the <hi>ſwifter:</hi> mens <hi>burning</hi> in unmortified luſts, while they are <hi>covering</hi> themſelves with <hi>aſhes</hi> turns the <hi>ſolemn
<pb facs="tcp:47281:3"/>meeting</hi> it ſelf into <hi>Iniquity:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.13.</note> ſuch a people will be <hi>brought lower</hi> for their pretended <hi>Humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and their formal <hi>Abſtinence</hi> ſhall <hi>fatten</hi> them for Judgment.</p>
            <p>There is nothing which will more betray the inſincerity of <hi>that day's</hi> ſervices, than the <hi>total diſcontinuance</hi> of them now; certainly the work, which we were then called to, could not be well done, by thoſe who thought it the <hi>work of a day; great congregrations</hi> are not the only places wherein the people of God are to <hi>pour out their hearts before him:</hi> nor is <hi>prayer</hi> at any time to be <hi>reſtrained,</hi> till God's favourable <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers</hi> ſtir us up to the <hi>offering of praiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 62.6.</note> 
               <hi>You that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence,</hi> ſhould be a continual remembrance to us of our continual duty; that as we have mourned <hi>together</hi> publickly, we may now privately <hi>mourn apart,</hi> and follow God as cloſe with our <hi>Single Petitions,</hi> while the cauſe remains, as we did for a few hours with our <hi>Joynt-Requeſts.</hi> So might the <hi>Kingdom of heaven ſuffer violence</hi> (as it were) from us, and neither the <hi>Gates of Hell,</hi> nor any <hi>Enemies upon earth</hi> be able to <hi>ſtand</hi> before us.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47281:4"/>
            <p>To this end, I <hi>very willingly</hi> bore a ſmall part in the late <hi>General ſolemnity,</hi> and ſhould be moſt glad, if I could contribute any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the <hi>unwilling publication</hi> of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon; for I muſt own my averſeneſs to this, as well as my readineſs to the other; but if that which the urgent intreaties of ſome (whoſe unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>affection</hi> to my perſon, may I hope, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them ſome <hi>good</hi> by my miniſtry) have extort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from me, ſhould iſſue in the awakening of any to their preſent duty, in <hi>ſeeking the Lord and his ſtrength</hi> upon ſo great and important an occaſion,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105 4.</note> I ſhall rejoyce on their behalf, and be encourag'd to <hi>diſpleaſe</hi> my ſelf more for the <hi>profiting</hi> of others, as well as to run the hazard of thoſe <hi>Imputations</hi> which <hi>Ill will</hi> is always apt to caſt.</p>
            <p>I have nothing more to detain the Reader in this place with, but to beg, that the Unaccurate <hi>manner</hi> of handling may not prejudice him againſt the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> it ſelf, and that he would not be offended with the <hi>thing</hi> for want of <hi>acceptable words:</hi> let all the weakneſſes here diſcover'd, be attributed to the <hi>man,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:47281:4"/>and if there be any thing truly Edifying and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, let the honour of it be given to <hi>God,</hi> who hath taught me to account my ſelf as one of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The meaneſt of his Servants, though in the Nobleſt Employment. <hi>T. C.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 19. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:47281:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47281:5"/>
            <head>The Churches <hi>Plea</hi> for the Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to Proſper <hi>Humane Force.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSALM 108.10, 11.</bibl>
                  <p>Who will bring me into the ſtrong City? Who will lead me into Edom?</p>
                  <p>Wilt not thou, Oh God, who haſt caſt us off? And wilt not thou, Oh God, go forth with our Hoſts?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis whole <hi>Pſalm,</hi> with very little variation of <hi>Words,</hi> and without the leaſt variation of <hi>Matter,</hi> is borrowed from <hi>two preceding</hi> Pſalms. The <hi>former part</hi> of it is compos'd of the latter part of the 57th. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> from the 7th. verſe to the end; the <hi>latter part</hi> is taken out of the 60th. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> from the 5th. verſe to the end. But whereas that (laſt mentioned) Pſalm is introduc'd with a moſt ſad and <hi>mournful Preface,</hi> holy <hi>David</hi> begins here in a more <hi>chearful ſtrain,</hi> as more ſuited to the <hi>preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation,</hi> under which he was. When <hi>that</hi> Pſalm was penn'd, <hi>David</hi> ſeems to have been in <hi>actual dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> at the writing of <hi>this</hi> he is thought to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Mercy,</hi> which he prayed for before; and he <hi>now</hi> records his own <hi>Experience</hi> of God's Goodneſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47281:6"/>to him, and powerful appearance for him in former difficulties and ſtraits, not only as a <hi>standing encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> to himſelf, and other beleivers then, but as a <hi>Typical pledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dickson</hi> on the Pſalms Vol. 3. p. 94.</note> and earneſt of that glorious final victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry which ſhould be obtained by the true <hi>Militant Church</hi> over all her inteſtine and foreign Enemies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>conduct of Christ</hi> her exalted Head and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the <hi>Goſpel Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>Davids particular Caſe</hi> was, we may eaſily collect from other Scriptures. Before the Death of <hi>Saul,</hi> he had the promiſe from God, of ſucceeding in the <hi>Throne,</hi> and of the proſperity and flouriſhing of his Kingdom; when he had the poſſeſſion of it, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>neighbouring Princes</hi> and Nations ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to oppoſe him; among the reſt, the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> did ſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 83.6, 7, 8.</note> and the <hi>Syrians,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites, Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Edomites,</hi> of whoſe Confederacy and conjunction in that accurſed Cauſe, the Holy Ghoſt gives us a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct account. <hi>David</hi>'s engagement in theſe juſt and neceſſary <hi>Wars</hi> againſt <hi>his,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Adverſaries (which were continued in ſome meaſure till the very <hi>birth of Solomon</hi>) was the reaſon why God did not expect from him the <hi>building of the Temple;</hi> but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, God did not <hi>leave him alone</hi> in the carrying of them on, and the conqueſts which he made, were very conſiderable, according to the <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> of his own Heart. <hi>Moab</hi> (ſays he, <hi>verſe</hi> 9. of this Pſalm) <hi>is my waſh-pot, and over Edom will I caſt out my ſhooe,</hi> (expreſſions of great <hi>Contempt,</hi> and of the meanneſs and <hi>ſervitude</hi> of that ſtate, which they ſhould be brought into) <hi>over Philiſtia will I triumph.</hi> So he proceeds in the words of the Text, <hi>who will bring me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:47281:6"/>
            <p>Some conceive, that by the <hi>[ſtrong City]</hi> here, in the 10th. verſe is meant <hi>Rabbah,</hi> the <hi>Royal City</hi> of the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> which was ſo long beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and at laſt taken by <hi>Joab.</hi> Others think,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.26.</note> that the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks to the <hi>ſame ſubject</hi> both in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and latter part of the verſe, and therefore apply it to the <hi>Fortifyed places</hi> in [<hi>Edom</hi>'s] Countrey, who boaſted much of invincible ſtrength; as we may learn from the Prophet, who foretelling the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Edom,</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">Obad. 3.</note> 
               <hi>The pride of thy heart hath deceived thee, thou that dwelleſt in the clefts of the rock, whoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation is high, that ſayeſt in thy heart, who ſhall bring me down to the ground?</hi> Theſe <hi>Edomites,</hi> as they were lofty and inſolent, ſo they were old and inveterate Enemies to the <hi>ſeed of Jacob;</hi> but <hi>David</hi> was <hi>led</hi> (as he wiſht) by a <hi>mighty hand</hi> of Providence to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh and ſubdue them;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 8.14.</note> ſo that <hi>throughout all Edom he put garriſons, and they all became David</hi>'s <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Time</hi> which he refers to, in the 11th. verſe wherein God <hi>[had caſt them off]</hi> was in the Reign of <hi>Saul,</hi> when the ſins of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were juſtly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, both by his <hi>Arbitrary practices,</hi> whom they fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly courted, and by God's <hi>abandoning</hi> of them, whom they ſinfully deſpis'd. <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Subjests</hi> could not but ſay, that it was <hi>better with them now</hi> in all reſpects, than heretofore; as they now lived under a more gentle and <hi>Righteous Government,</hi> ſo they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed more of the ſmiles and <hi>bleſſings of Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words contain in them two principal things. 1. An earneſt <hi>enquiry</hi> after ſome effectual <hi>ſuccour. Who will bring me into the ſtrong City? Who will lead me into Edom?</hi> Not that <hi>David was ignorant,</hi> whence
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47281:7"/>ſuch ſuccour might be had, like the <hi>blind world</hi> whoſe <hi>common cry</hi> is,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>who will ſhew us any good?</hi> (for he had an <hi>Eye</hi> which was always <hi>open,</hi> to the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Hills</hi>) but to intimate, that he <hi>depended not</hi> upon any <hi>Military preparations,</hi> not upon any skill and courage of <hi>his own,</hi> nor upon the numbers and union of <hi>his people.</hi> The like paſſage we meet with elſewhere;<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.19.</note> 
               <hi>Who will riſe up for me againſt the evil doers? Or who will stand up for me againſt the workers of Iniquity?</hi> Implying, that he wanted and ſought after ſome further help, beyond what he had already, in the concurrence of his <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Allyes,</hi> whoſe ſervice, though valuable and uſeful in its place, was not ſufficient. 2. An Humble <hi>expostulation</hi> with God about it. <hi>Wilt not thou, Oh God, who haſt caſt us off? And wilt not thou oh God, go forth with our Hoſts? David</hi> forms his <hi>Petition</hi> into a <hi>Queſtion,</hi> which he puts up to God with a <hi>becoming reverence,</hi> and yet with a <hi>warrantable boldneſs;</hi> as in other places alſo,<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.6.</note> after the ſame manner; <hi>wilt not thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive us again, that thy people may rejoyce in thee?</hi> Which was no argument of any <hi>distruſt,</hi> or doubt whether God would or no, but rather on the other hand ſignified an <hi>hopeful confidence</hi> that he would. I will only add, that this is ſuch a <hi>way of Addreſs</hi> to God, as the <hi>due modesty</hi> of <hi>Creatures</hi> and <hi>Sinners</hi> does not forbid, but the <hi>Liberty</hi> granted to <hi>beleivers</hi> does very much encourage.</p>
            <p>There are ſeveral Truths included in this Text, which are worthy to be opened, and <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> at this Day.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:47281:7"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, That <hi>In Caſes of publick Commotion, by the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts which Enemies make againſt us, and we againſt them, it behoves us to be very ſollicitous about the iſſue of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Secondly, That <hi>Former rejection by God ſhould not damp all comfortable expectation of future aſſiſtance from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, That <hi>God's favourable help is of greateſt conſequence to be deſired and obtain'd for the making of our Arms Victorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I propoſe to handle theſe points <hi>ſeverally,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with an Application which may be ſuitable to <hi>them all,</hi> and to the deſign of this dayes Aſſembly.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> Thing, which I ſhall endeavour to ſhew, is that <hi>In caſes of publick commotion, when our Enemies and we are making mutual attempts againſt each other, we ought to be very ſollicitous, that it may have an happy and ſucceſsful end.</hi> This truth is grounded upon the paſſionate working of <hi>David</hi>'s Spirit, when his Forces were bent againſt <hi>bloudy Edom,</hi> he ſeems to be <hi>zealous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inquiſitive</hi> about the matter, <hi>Who will bring me into the ſtrong City?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>We ſhould not, like <hi>Jonah, ſleep</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Storms,</hi> but <hi>rowſe</hi> our ſelves into a ſerious thoughtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as to <hi>what will become</hi> of us and of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. We know how <hi>ſharp</hi> the Diſciples were upon our Saviour, when the waves beat into the Ship, and he lay upon a pillow in the hinder part of it;<note place="margin">Mark 4.38.</note> 
                  <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter careſt thou not that we periſh?</hi> What cenſure then can be too ſevere for thoſe, who in the <hi>greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe of Nations,</hi> do ſcarcely manifeſt the <hi>leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern?</hi> Though perhaps <hi>more than a Kingdom</hi> lyes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47281:8"/>under the hazard of periſhing, there are multitudes of ſuch a <hi>ſlothful</hi> and <hi>careleſs</hi> temper, that they will not put themſelves to the <hi>trouble of conſidering;</hi> but <hi>ſit at caſe,</hi> till almoſt every thing about them is not only <hi>ſhaken</hi> but <hi>removed.</hi> How many, as if they were <hi>ſtrangers in our Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>worſe,</hi> have no ſenſe of the <hi>common difficulties</hi> to be encountred, nor of the <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> to be eſcap'd; but at the ſame time, when all good men are ready to <hi>ſtand with their hands upon their Loins,</hi> or to <hi>fall upon their Knees,</hi> they are perfectly ſtupid and ſecure, and ſhake off all <hi>fear of wrath</hi> in this World as well as that which is to come! Surely this is not a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> but a <hi>brutiſh</hi> frame; a frame moſt unfit to be found in <hi>now,</hi> when ſuch <hi>probable dangers</hi> look us in the face, when both the rage and confidence of our Enemies is grown ſo high, and our own unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>freſh deliverances</hi> is ſo notorious. To be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of our preſent circumſtances, or indifferent about them, argues an <hi>Heart</hi> wofully <hi>hardned,</hi> and is a <hi>ſin</hi> which hath <hi>various ſins</hi> in it. I ſhall mention <hi>Three</hi> which are very evident.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, It carries in it a <hi>contempt of Providence.</hi> For there is the <hi>finger of God</hi> in every <hi>Hand</hi> which is lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up againſt us; no <hi>Dog</hi> can <hi>move his Tongue</hi> againſt an <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> if God think fit to <hi>tye</hi> it; no <hi>man</hi> can ſo much as <hi>deſire our Land,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34.24.</note> if he would <hi>reſtrain</hi> and bridle their Affections. God can <hi>chain up</hi> the ambition, or the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, the pride or the fury, which is in the hearts of Tyrants, tho he never intend to <hi>purge it out.</hi> Satan and all his Inſtruments, being God's <hi>priſoners,</hi> are limited &amp; <hi>confined</hi> by him, according as he pleaſes; and therefore if they be in any meaſure <hi>let looſe,</hi> 'tis a ſpecial diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation which calls us to <hi>bethink our ſelves.</hi> Neither the <hi>roaring Lyon,</hi> nor any other <hi>Beaſts of prey</hi> can <hi>go
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47281:8"/>about, ſeeking whom they may devour,</hi> much leſs could they <hi>actually</hi> devour, if God would <hi>hedge them in.</hi> Without his permiſſion, the <hi>waſter</hi> cannot <hi>find in his heart to deſtroy,</hi> nor lay his <hi>deſign,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.16.</note> nor <hi>do any thing</hi> in order to its accompliſhment; for God hath <hi>created the waſter,</hi> as ſuch. It is in his power, when he will, to <hi>ſeal up the hand of every man;</hi> therefore,<note place="margin">Job 37.7.</note> when wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men are ſuffered to <hi>diſturb</hi> our peace, and we are put to <hi>defend</hi> our ſelves by force, 'tis an awakening ſummons to ſerious conſideration. He that could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Balaam</hi> from <hi>curſing</hi> his people, can as eaſily hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der other Adverſaries from <hi>aſſaulting</hi> them; he that <hi>moved</hi> the Officers in the <hi>Syrian</hi> Army to <hi>depart from Jehoſhaphat,</hi> after they had <hi>ſurrounded</hi> him,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 18.31.</note> is as able to keep them from <hi>coming nigh.</hi> The God, who <hi>gathers the wind in his fiſts,</hi> could block up the moſt threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Fleets</hi> on their <hi>own ſhores;</hi> undoubtedly then, if he <hi>fill their Sails,</hi> and give them the opportunity of advancing towards <hi>ours,</hi> it ought to ſeize and affect our minds. 'Tis good to take heed, leſt in <hi>deſpiſing</hi> the opoſition of <hi>man</hi> ſometimes, we deſpiſe the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it diſcovers a want of <hi>Compaſſion to our Brethren.</hi> We know that the <hi>War</hi> now undertaken, is deſign'd for the relief of our <hi>Fellow-Proteſtants,</hi> as well as our own ſafety: ſo that if this ſhould fail and miſcarry, we cannot without horror reflect upon the fatal conſequences of it, with reſpect to <hi>them,</hi> as well as our ſelves. If the <hi>unclean Spirit</hi> be not <hi>caſt-out</hi> he will <hi>torment</hi> thoſe poor creatures ſo much the <hi>more,</hi> which are already under his power. If our Enemyes ſhould have the ſucceſſe which we pray againſt, it would make their <hi>little fingers thicker and heavier than their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47281:9"/>loins</hi> have yet been: and wo be to thoſe whom God ſhall give up to fall under <hi>half that weight.</hi> When <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> did but intercede with <hi>Pharoah:</hi> that the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might go and ſacrifice to God in the wilderneſs,<note place="margin">Exod. 5.7.</note> he preſently <hi>increas't their task, and multiplyed their burdens;</hi> what do we then ſuppoſe, that he would have done, if he could have <hi>overtaken</hi> them in his <hi>purſuit</hi> of them, and <hi>brought them back</hi> into his Land? It is a <hi>double deſtruction</hi> which our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren muſt look for, if God ſhould blaſt our attempts to <hi>ſave</hi> them. And beſides, they are our <hi>Brethren</hi> alſo, who adventure and expoſe their lives in this Cauſe, whether in the <hi>field,</hi> or the <hi>deep:</hi> they are many of them (as the tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid to <hi>David</hi>) <hi>our bone and our fleſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 5.1.</note> and their <hi>Death</hi> ſhould be <hi>precious in our ſight</hi> upon that account. How does every man, that really engages in this great Expedition, <hi>carry his ſoul in his hand,</hi> and throw himſelf upon the ſenſible brink of Eternity? Not one of thoſe many Thouſands knows, but that the <hi>price of his bloud</hi> may be written upon the mercy which is brought forth: ſhould we not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be very thoughtful about the <hi>gaining</hi> of that mercy, which multitudes may <hi>pay ſo dearly</hi> for? <hi>Is it nothing to us,</hi> that in all likelihood, the <hi>ſword</hi> muſt <hi>cut off</hi> ſo many of our <hi>Friends,</hi> before we are fully delivered from our <hi>Enemies?</hi> where is our Humanity and the <hi>ſounding of our bowels?</hi> are they all <hi>ſhut up?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thirdly, it betrayes want of <hi>zeal for the intereſt of Chriſt.</hi> There is a great deal more which <hi>lyes at ſtake</hi> this day, than perhaps we are all aware of at the firſt ſight: according as God <hi>ſhines upon</hi> our <hi>counſels,</hi> or <hi>overthrows</hi> them, according as he bleſſes, or defeats what is now doing, for ought we know, it may fare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47281:9"/>
                  <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill</hi> with the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and with all that adhere to it: (at leaſt, <hi>all</hi> in theſe parts of the world.) God himſelf only is able to tell, how far the conſequence of this preſent action may extend, as to the <hi>raiſing</hi> or <hi>ruining,</hi> the <hi>Supporting</hi> or <hi>Extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the Reformed profeſſion. There is manifeſtly that <hi>upon the wheel,</hi> which as God is pleaſed to order and determine it, may turn the ſcale very much as to the fall of <hi>Sion</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> the upholding of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>Antichrist,</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> The iſſue of it, is likely to be very <hi>glorious,</hi> or very <hi>diſmal:</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> will either <hi>get</hi> or <hi>loſe</hi> much ground: <hi>Truth</hi> will be quite <hi>Eclips't</hi> and Swallowed up by <hi>Strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions,</hi> or elſe prevail and <hi>triumph</hi> over them. Some where (Either in the <hi>Land of Judah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 26.1.</note> or in the land of her Enemies) that <hi>Song</hi> will be ſung, <hi>We have a ſtrong City.</hi> If our Adverſaries ſhould be permitted to <hi>lift up their heads</hi> now, how will they <hi>trample</hi> our <hi>Holy faith</hi> under their <hi>feet?</hi> what <hi>havock</hi> and <hi>deſolations</hi> will they make, whereſoever the <hi>name</hi> of Chriſt is duly <hi>call'd upon?</hi> how would the Conqueſt of <hi>theſe Kingdomes,</hi> and of thoſe <hi>Provinces</hi> that have ſo ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably aſſiſted us (which God in mercy forbid) <hi>let them in like a flood</hi> upon the reſt of the true <hi>Chriſtian world?</hi> They would no longer ſay, <hi>let us break their bands in ſunder,</hi> but conclude, that they <hi>had broken</hi> them, and bid us in deriſion, to <hi>flee as a bird to our moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.1.</note> This in the judgment of reaſon muſt follow, if God ſhould caſt the <hi>lot of Victory</hi> on their ſide: and therefore, <hi>is there not a cauſe</hi> for the deepeſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? muſt we not be (like the <hi>Idols</hi> of our Enemies,) <hi>ſtocks</hi> and <hi>ſtones in deed,</hi> if we ſit ſtill and conſider
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47281:10"/>nothing, when the <hi>All of our Religion</hi> ſeems Embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu'd in this bottom?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> thing, which I am to prove, is that <hi>Former rejection by God ſhould not diſcourage all Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able expectation of future aſſiſtance.</hi> The God that <hi>hath caſt us off</hi> heretofore (as we ſee here in the text) may ſtand by us, and joyn with us afterwards. We are not to think that the <hi>ſtream</hi> of adverſe Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will never <hi>turn,</hi> or that he who ſeems to forget our miſery <hi>a while,</hi> will forget it <hi>always.</hi> If God hath been <hi>angry,</hi> we muſt not therefore fancy, that he is <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable;</hi> if his <hi>fury hath burnt like fire,</hi> it is no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this fire <hi>cannot be quenched.</hi> Such conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are very abſurd and irrational upon ſeveral ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. I ſhall inſtance in <hi>five Particulars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Providences</hi> in this world are very <hi>vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi> This is a <hi>changeable ſtate;</hi> the <hi>face of the Skie</hi> is not conſtantly alike, but ſometimes <hi>clear,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>lowring</hi>: 'tis neither always free from <hi>Clouds,</hi> nor always <hi>Covered</hi> with them. The Church from the beginning had her <hi>mixture</hi> of proſperous and afflictive dayes. As <hi>Job</hi> rebuk't his <hi>wife</hi> with ſaying, <hi>ſhall we receive good at the hands of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 2.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and not evil?</hi> ſo on the other hand we may comfort our ſelves with this, Have we received <hi>evil</hi> at Gods hands, and ſhall we not alſo receive <hi>good?</hi> (though there be this diſparity, that the one is <hi>freely</hi> beſtowed, and the other <hi>juſtly</hi> inflicted.) As it is groundleſs <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,</hi> when our <hi>mountain ſtands ſtrong,</hi> to ſay, we ſhall <hi>never be moved;</hi> ſo 'tis unreaſonable <hi>deſpair,</hi> when our Mountain hath been <hi>ſhaken,</hi> to ſay, we ſhall never be <hi>ſetled.</hi> Tho God is of <hi>one mind,</hi> and hath <hi>one general end,</hi> which is, to order and diſpoſe all things for the <hi>beſt,</hi> yet his Infinite <hi>wiſedom</hi> does not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47281:10"/>conſtantly obſerve one and the <hi>ſame method</hi>: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times he glorifies <hi>himſelf,</hi> and does <hi>us</hi> good by our <hi>distreſſes,</hi> and at other times by our <hi>deliverance.</hi> The <hi>Beauty</hi> of Divine Providences conſiſts partly in their <hi>Variety:</hi> the work of God would be leſſe admirable,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.11.</note> and his glory leſſe viſible, if His people were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually either under <hi>Smiling,</hi> or <hi>frowning</hi> Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, God hath his peculiar <hi>ſet times</hi> of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting judgment, and of ſhewing compaſſion. There is a <hi>time</hi> to correct, and there is likewiſe a <hi>time to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.13.</note> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes that there is <hi>a time of War,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and a time of peace.</hi> God obſerves the proper <hi>ſeaſons</hi> of giving <hi>reſt,</hi> and cauſing <hi>trouble,</hi> of exerciſing us <hi>with</hi> Enemies, and reſcuing us <hi>from</hi> them; and this he is as careful to do, as to maintain and keep up the ſucceſſion of <hi>day</hi> and <hi>night,</hi> of the <hi>Summers heat,</hi> and the <hi>Winters cold. Our Heavenly Father knows that we have need</hi> of both, and he knows <hi>when</hi> we need them; ſo that our <hi>Tranquillity</hi> ſhall not be <hi>lengthned out</hi> too far, nor the <hi>rod of the oppreſſour remain</hi> too long, but theſe things ſhall <hi>take their turns,</hi> as God ſees moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for us.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.23.</note> What the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſays with reſpect to the <hi>Reſurrection, every man in his own order,</hi> may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to this caſe, every thing falls out <hi>in its own order;</hi> when one work is <hi>accompliſhed,</hi> God <hi>begins</hi> another; when we have been kept low <hi>long enough</hi> in the midſt of difficulties and ſtraits, he Commands en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement to ariſe. Therefore, 'tis no ſtrange thing for God to <hi>remember mercy in wrath,</hi> and make <hi>light to ſhine out of darkneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos. 5.8.</note> and to <hi>turn the ſhadow of death into the morning.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:47281:11"/>
               <p>Thirdly, It is no unuſual thing for <hi>mercy</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> a peoples ſufferings, and <hi>overrule</hi> the arguments which are brought by <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Though we cannot ſay, that God is ever really <hi>divided againſt himſelf,</hi> yet when he condeſcends to ſpeak of himſelf <hi>after our manner,</hi> and in compliance with our infirmity, we read of a kind of <hi>ſtruggling</hi> and contention between one Attribute and another.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>How ſhall I give thee up, Ephraim?</hi> (ſays God by the <hi>Prophet</hi>) <hi>how ſhall I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thee, Iſrael?</hi> (as if he were vehemently preſs't to do it, and yet could not comply.) &amp;c. <hi>My heart is turned within me, my repentings are kindled together; I will not execute the fierceneſs of mine anger, I will not return to deſtroy Ephraim,</hi> &amp;c. The Righteouſneſs and the Goodneſs of God ſeemed here to be at variance, and after ſome diſpute (as it were) the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of God reſolved to <hi>ceaſe</hi> that controverſie, which his <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> might have <hi>continued; the people were bent to back ſliding from God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 7.</note> and therefore Juſtice was inclined to puniſh them ſtill; but mercy (like the <hi>Angel</hi> which held <hi>Abraham</hi>'s hand, when he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſacrifice <hi>his Son</hi>) urg'd their forbearance, and prevailed. God is often <hi>provok't</hi> by a Nations <hi>ſins</hi> to prolong thoſe calamities, which he uſes his <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of Grace</hi> in cutting ſhort. We generally deſerve that God ſhould <hi>pluck us down,</hi> and <hi>root us up,</hi> when on the contrary, 'tis his good pleaſure to <hi>build</hi> and to <hi>plant</hi> us. Indeed he never yet wrought any <hi>Salvation</hi> for his Church, but that at the ſame time, when he did ſo, he might have gone on in the <hi>way of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, There is the leſs reaſon to look upon former Rejections as <hi>final,</hi> when the <hi>cauſes</hi> of them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47281:11"/>are in ſome meaſure <hi>removed.</hi> Perhaps, God <hi>caſt us off</hi> before, for the ſake of ſome <hi>National wickedneſſes,</hi> which are at this day <hi>purg'd.</hi> It could not be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that God ſhould upon any occaſion <hi>fight for us,</hi> when the <hi>body of the people</hi> in the ſame manner which <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſpoke of, were <hi>fighting againſt God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 5.39.</note> While the <hi>Word of God</hi> (in a ſenſe) was <hi>bound,</hi> I mean, while the preaching of it was reſtrained, no wonder that God was <hi>as a man astonied,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jerem. 14.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and as a mighty man that could not ſave.</hi> It is in vain to hide that which is too publickly known, and calls for <hi>ſolemn Repentance;</hi> the ſin of <hi>Perſecution</hi> (that <hi>miſchief framed by a Law</hi>) was for many years, like <hi>Achan's accurſed thing</hi> in our <hi>Camps;</hi> but God having now by the <hi>hands of our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators</hi> opened a <hi>door</hi> for the free progreſs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel among our ſelves, one great <hi>obſtacle</hi> of our Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs againſt Foreign Enemies is <hi>taken out of the way.</hi> A <hi>Legal Indulgence</hi> to Tender Conſciences was as fit a preparative to this <hi>Faſt,</hi> as this Faſt is to the <hi>following War.</hi> I might add, that it may be, ſometimes <hi>God went not forth</hi> with our Hoſts, becauſe <hi>they</hi> went forth, not againſt our <hi>Popiſh,</hi> but our <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; when we were joyning with our <hi>Enemies</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>Friends</hi> it was in <hi>Mercy</hi> to us, that God did not proſper us; when we have been <hi>helping</hi> thoſe who ſought our <hi>ruine,</hi> and <hi>weakening</hi> thoſe that were always our <hi>refuge in diſtreſs,</hi> the <hi>aſſistance</hi> of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence would have argued his <hi>diſpleaſure;</hi> but bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, that now they who are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> with us in one <hi>Faith,</hi> are alſo joyned in one <hi>Intereſt</hi> and <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and therefore we may ſomewhat better expect God's <hi>Conjunction</hi> with us now than heretofore.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47281:12"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Thoſe <hi>bitter things</hi> which God hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>written againſt</hi> us, we may <hi>read</hi> a great deal of <hi>comfort</hi> in, upon our return to God. The <hi>Wine of aſtoniſhment</hi> which we have taſted, may now be made a <hi>refreſhing Cordial.</hi> For Executions of <hi>Treatenings</hi> (as <hi>One</hi> well obſerves) ſhould be taken as pawns of the performance of <hi>promiſes;</hi> the ſame unalterable <hi>Truth</hi> which binds to the one, will ſecure the other. We may be confident, that God was not more ready to <hi>forſake</hi> us during our <hi>Impenitency,</hi> than he is to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive</hi> us, when we <hi>repent. Past calamities</hi> while we were in our ſins, ſhould be improved to <hi>ſtrengthen our Faith</hi> of <hi>future mercies,</hi> when we turn from our ſins. If God hath <hi>in faithfulneſs afflicted us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.75.</note> why ſhould we queſtion his Faithfulneſs in <hi>releiving</hi> us? We that have felt the <hi>laſhes</hi> of his angry <hi>rod,</hi> when we were running from him, ſhall undoubtedly experience the <hi>ſuccours</hi> of his <hi>mighty Arm,</hi> when we come back to him. Sinners, whoſe <hi>Tranſgreſſions have been viſited,</hi> are of all others the moſt likely to be pitied, when they become penitents. The remembrance of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>wounds,</hi> ſeems to be an encouraging motive to the Church to look for a gracious <hi>Cure; Come, and let us return unto the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note> 
                  <hi>for he hath torn, and he will heal us; q. d.</hi> he will heal <hi>the rather,</hi> becauſe he hath torn us. If God had not caſt us off <hi>before,</hi> we ſhould have more reaſon to be jealous, that he would do it <hi>now.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Thing which I undertook to ſhew, is that <hi>God's favourable help is of moſt importance to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and obtained for the making of our Arms Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47281:12"/>
               <p>'Tis true, that <hi>ſecond Cauſes</hi> have their proper <hi>Sphere</hi> to <hi>Act</hi> in, but the <hi>first</hi> is infinitely <hi>above</hi> them. God does not accuſtom himſelf in theſe dayes to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der means <hi>unneceſſary</hi> by Miracles, but he renders them <hi>efficacious</hi> by the concurrent exerciſe of his own power. As God does not <hi>raiſe up children to Abraham from the stones,</hi> but propagates an holy Seed in an <hi>ordinary way;</hi> ſo he does not defend us meerly by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible <hi>Legions of Angels,</hi> when there are <hi>Men</hi> to be employed for ſuch a purpoſe. When God was about to make <hi>David</hi> King, in ſpite of all his oppoſers, he ſo turn'd the hearts of the <hi>Tribes of Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Chro. 12.22.</note> that they <hi>came to him to help him day by day, till it was a great Hoſt, like the Host of God.</hi> He that <hi>rules in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Heaven,</hi> makes uſe of Armies upon <hi>Earth</hi> too, and manages their <hi>military acts</hi> for the fulfilling of his own ends. God ſpeaks of <hi>commanding,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 13.3, 4, 5.</note> and <hi>calling his ſanctified ones,</hi> and <hi>muſtering them for the battail,</hi> and making them <hi>the weapons of his indignation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the Land of Babylon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 5.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> appeared as <hi>chief Captain of the Host of the Lord,</hi> when <hi>Joſhua</hi> was their viſible <hi>Leader.</hi> The <hi>ſword of the Lord</hi> had the preheminence,<note place="margin">Judg. 7.18.</note> when the <hi>ſword of Gideon</hi> was drawn alſo. Though <hi>David</hi> went as <hi>Champion</hi> againſt <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah,</hi> he gives the glory of thoſe Titles to God, <hi>the Lord of Hoſts, the God of the Armies of Iſrael.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.45.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cries out here in the <hi>Text</hi> to God, <hi>Wilt not thou go forth with our Hosts?</hi> alluding (as ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) to God's <hi>marching</hi> before the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the <hi>cloudy Pillar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.7.</note> which was an Emblem and <hi>Token</hi> of his preſence. Indeed, 'tis the <hi>preſence</hi> or <hi>abſence</hi> of God, which makes the event of all <hi>Warlike Expeditions</hi> either <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad; Deborah</hi> animates <hi>Barak</hi> with this, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47281:13"/>
                  <hi>Siſera</hi> would certainly <hi>fall into his hand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 4.14.</note> becauſe the <hi>Lord was gone out before him;</hi> and on the other ſide, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> complains, that God <hi>made them turn back from the Enemy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.9, 10.</note> becauſe <hi>he went not along with them.</hi> Creatures like our ſelves, have <hi>their part</hi> to perform but Almighty <hi>Aids</hi> are the <hi>principal thing.</hi> Upon this account, <hi>Moſes</hi> was not contented with the guidance of an <hi>Angel,</hi> without the preſence of God himſelf; <hi>If thy preſence go not with me,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 33.15.</note> 
                  <hi>carry us not up hence;</hi> implying, that it was to no purpoſe for them to <hi>move,</hi> if they <hi>left their God behind</hi> them. God's <hi>going forth</hi> with Armies, is eminently advantagious to them in ſeveral reſpects; which I ſhall reduce to theſe four <hi>Heads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, By enduing them with <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> for their proper work. Multitudes of perſons are call'd to this ſervice, that were never <hi>trained up</hi> (it may be) by tedious diſcipline, nor have had opportunity of <hi>improving</hi> themſelves by frequent practiſe, according to the <hi>methods</hi> and <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>Art,</hi> whom God (never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs) can <hi>inſtruct to diſcretion</hi> in this employment, as he does the <hi>Husbandman</hi> in his.<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.26.</note> He who is <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful in Counſel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 29.</note> as well as <hi>excellent in working,</hi> does therefore many times <hi>chuſe</hi> even in this caſe, <hi>the fooliſh things of the World to confound the wiſe;</hi> men that have but little <hi>experience,</hi> and as little <hi>wiſdom</hi> of ſuch a ſort, to foil the greateſt <hi>Commanders</hi> with.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.33.</note> What was <hi>David</hi> but a <hi>raw ſtripling,</hi> that ran from the <hi>Sheepfold</hi> to the <hi>Camp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">c. 18.5.</note> and in a little while, he was <hi>ſet over the men of War,</hi> and made himſelf ſo famous, that the <hi>ſlaying of ten thouſands</hi> was <hi>aſcribed to him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 7.</note> and but <hi>thouſands to Saul;</hi> the true cauſe of which is mentioned afterwards,<note place="margin">v. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord was with him.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47281:13"/>makes a particular acknowledgment of it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord my ſtrength, which teacheth my hands to war, and my fingers to fight.</hi> He that underſtood only how to <hi>handle a Crook,</hi> or <hi>play upon a Harp,</hi> muſt needs be <hi>taught of God,</hi> when he came to meddle with <hi>weapons of War.</hi> God can make thoſe men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable <hi>Helpers</hi> in a victorious Battel, whoſe Folly and Ignorance we might rather ſuſpect to <hi>hinder</hi> it.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, By <hi>Inſpiring</hi> them with <hi>Courage.</hi> That God who hath put ſuch a <hi>Nature</hi> into the <hi>Horſe</hi> (which being a <hi>Brute,</hi> is not capable of the ſame impreſſions as a <hi>Man</hi>) that <hi>He mocketh at fear,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 39.22, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>and is not affrighted, neither turneth he back from the ſword,</hi> &amp;c. What a <hi>vigour</hi> can he eaſily <hi>diffuſe</hi> by his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen influence into the <hi>ſpirits</hi> of reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? It is thought, that <hi>Balaam</hi> refers to this, when he ſays concerning <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 23.21.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord his God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is among them.</hi> The Preſence of God with a People creates ſuch an extraordinary chearfulneſs and joy, as when a Juſt and Gracious <hi>Prince</hi> comes into the <hi>Field,</hi> and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by his <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> with Univerſal <hi>Acclamations;</hi> it fills them with ſuch <hi>Life,</hi> that they can <hi>look</hi> innumerable <hi>Deaths</hi> in the <hi>face,</hi> without <hi>paleneſs,</hi> or dejection; they value nothing that ſtands in their way, having the Encouragement of ſuch a Leader. There is no <hi>ſuch fortitude</hi> in the World, as that which proceeds from <hi>this very cauſe;</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Souldier does far exceed the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;</hi> for a <hi>Divine Principle</hi> and Motive muſt needs carry men a great deal further than a <hi>Moral.</hi> What <hi>hardſhips</hi> will he rejoyce to endure, what <hi>dangers</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:47281:14"/>will he prepare to meet, who <hi>feels</hi> an <hi>Immanuel,</hi> God with him! How does this ſtrengthen mens <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Hands,</hi> and raiſe them to a <hi>more than Heroick</hi> pitch! This quicken'd <hi>Jael</hi> (one of the <hi>feebler ſex</hi>) to do execution upon the <hi>mighty Siſera;</hi> and hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prompted <hi>ſmall Handfuls</hi> of men to be the <hi>bold Aſſailants</hi> of the moſt <hi>unequal numbers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by the <hi>prevention</hi> of Enemies from mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any <hi>remarkable reſistance.</hi> This God does, where he is preſent, two wayes; <hi>viz.</hi> in <hi>blinding,</hi> and <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, In the <hi>blinding</hi> of Enemies. I do not mean <hi>Literally,</hi> as God did to the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> who would have offer'd violence to <hi>Lot,</hi> and to the <hi>King of</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's <hi>Troopers</hi> that were ſent to apprehend <hi>Eliſha;</hi> but in <hi>confounding</hi> and perplexing of all their Counſels and Deſigns, and bereaving them of the <hi>uſe</hi> of that <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and cunning which they have. When <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi>'s <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> was <hi>grown strong</hi> againſt his Father, God ſecured <hi>David</hi> by turning the ſubtle and <hi>politick</hi> advices of <hi>Achitophel</hi> into <hi>fooliſhneſs;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.31.</note> and this was the way of Eſcape which <hi>David</hi> himſelf ſought for; becauſe if <hi>Abſalom</hi> had follow'd that courſe which <hi>Achitophel</hi> chalk't out, <hi>David</hi> in all probability had loſt the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> God firſt <hi>infatuates</hi> thoſe, whom he intends to <hi>overthrow;</hi> he <hi>ſhuts their Eyes</hi> that they may not <hi>find their hands;</hi> he throws their reaſon and judgment into a <hi>dead ſleep,</hi> and ſo <hi>hurries</hi> their <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted</hi> thoughts, that they cannot think <hi>one thought</hi> to their advantage. If God be <hi>on our ſide,</hi> he will make thoſe that are <hi>against us</hi> to take thoſe methods, whereby they ſhall <hi>destroy themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, In the <hi>terrifying</hi> of them. There are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47281:14"/>many Inſtances of this in Scripture. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> had their <hi>Chariot wheels taken off</hi> in the <hi>Red Sea</hi> by Gods <hi>troubling</hi> of them,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.24, 25.</note> and the dreadful apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>his fighting for Iſrael.</hi> And ſo it was <hi>propheſied</hi> many years after this, that <hi>Egypt ſhould tremble,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 19.16.</note> 
                  <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſhaking of the hand of the Lord of hoſts.</hi> The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were ſcared with the ſenſe of <hi>Gods coming into the Iſraelitiſh camp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.7.</note> when they ſhouted at the arrival of the Ark. <hi>Saul</hi> was perfectly <hi>diſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated,</hi> and loſt the Spirit which he once had, when <hi>God was departed from him;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">chap. 31.4.</note> and in the end became his <hi>own murderer,</hi> for fear of <hi>dying by another.</hi> So eaſie a matter is it, for God to change the very <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers</hi> of men from the greateſt <hi>Courage,</hi> to the moſt ſordid and ſhameful <hi>cowardiſe;</hi> as is ſaid in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>the mighty men of Babylon have forborn to fight,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 51.30.</note> 
                  <hi>they have remained in their holds, their might hath failed, they became as women.</hi> An Omnipotent God can in a moment <hi>take away the hearts</hi> of the ſtouteſt Enemies; and by that means diſ-able them from making that oppoſition which they would.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, By <hi>Ordering</hi> and <hi>Governing</hi> of thoſe things which appear moſt <hi>caſual</hi> and <hi>contingent</hi> unto us. Thoſe things which are <hi>wholly</hi> out of our power, God can make to ſerve his and our purpoſe. As the ſame <hi>Waters</hi> which ſtood up like a <hi>Wall</hi> for the <hi>Iſrael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites</hi> of old, and fell down again for a <hi>Grave</hi> to the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> ſo God can now cauſe the ſame <hi>Sea</hi> to <hi>bear</hi> our <hi>Ships,</hi> and to <hi>bury</hi> theirs. A <hi>ſtorm,</hi> when he pleaſes, can bring about his end, and our deſire; and with this <hi>breath of his mouth,</hi> in the <hi>twin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling of an eye,</hi> he can do that, which many united
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47281:15"/>
                  <hi>hands</hi> cannot in the compaſs of weeks or months. Every <hi>bullet</hi> that's <hi>ſhot,</hi> ſhall <hi>enter</hi> where God <hi>directs</hi> it, and the <hi>ſteadieſt aims</hi> of men ſignifie nothing in compariſon of the <hi>Eye of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that <hi>covers the heads</hi> of his Friends and Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, can <hi>lay open the bodies</hi> of his Enemies, as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>mark</hi> for <hi>Inſtruments of</hi> Cruelty. The Man that <hi>drew a bow at a venture,</hi> ſmote the <hi>King of Iſrael,</hi> though in a diſguiſe,<note place="margin">1 King. 22.34.</note> 
                  <hi>between the joints of the Harneſs,</hi> becauſe it was God that <hi>guided the Arrow.</hi> So when the <hi>ſtone</hi> out of <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>ſling</hi> ſunk into <hi>Goliah</hi>'s <hi>fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> which prov'd his mortal wound, and the rout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the whole Hoſt of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> we read, it was <hi>God</hi> that <hi>gave him into</hi> his peoples Hands.<note place="margin">5 Sam. 17.47.</note> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents ſeemingly moſt <hi>uncertain,</hi> as well as <hi>minute</hi> and inconſiderable, carry a <hi>great ſtroke</hi> in <hi>determining of Victories,</hi> when God <hi>goes forth with our Armies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well might therefore the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> conclude this <hi>Pſalm</hi> after ſuch a manner;<note place="margin">ver. 12, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Give us help from trouble, for vain is the help of man;</hi> (not vain in conjunction <hi>with</hi> God, but vain <hi>without</hi> him). <hi>Through God we ſhall do valiantly</hi> (we are the immediate <hi>Agents,</hi> but he furniſhes with the <hi>active power,</hi> and brings forth the <hi>happy effect</hi>) <hi>for he it is that ſhall tread down our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>Having thus finiſhed the <hi>Doctrinal</hi> matter contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe words, I come now to make ſome <hi>Practical Improvement</hi> of it, with a ſpecial reference to the <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> of this Day. This may be beſt done in the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering</hi> of <hi>Two Questions;</hi> one of which tends to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us of our preſent <hi>Duty,</hi> the other will ſupply us with <hi>Arguments</hi> to back it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="question">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:47281:15"/>
                  <head>Quest. I.</head>
                  <p>The firſt Queſtion is, <hi>What ſhall we do,</hi> that our <hi>Pleadings</hi> with God in ſuch a Caſe, for his Conduct of us into <hi>Edom,</hi> and his Preſence with our Hoſts, may be <hi>effectual?</hi> Anſw. In ſix particulars.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, A neceſſary Rule to be obſerved, is, to <hi>ſeek firſt the pardon</hi> of our paſt ſins, and <hi>Reconciliation</hi> to our offended God. This is the inlet and <hi>introduction</hi> to all other Mercies, which are <hi>Mercies indeed;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> does not onely take notice of God's <hi>bringing back the captivity of Jacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſ. 85.1, 2, 3.</note> but that he had <hi>forgiven the iniquity of his people,</hi> and <hi>taken away all his wrath.</hi> There is no <hi>true temporal Bleſſing,</hi> but what is the fruit of this <hi>ſpiritual</hi> one. A <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> God may providentially deliver an <hi>unpardoned</hi> People, but 'tis a <hi>Curſe</hi> to them, rather than a Bleſſing; their eſcape out of Calamity is a <hi>greater ſnare,</hi> than if they had fallen into it.<note place="margin">Job 19.29.</note> 
                     <hi>Wrath brings the puniſhment of the Sword;</hi> if wrath therefore <hi>abides,</hi> after the Sword is <hi>put up,</hi> the Nation will be miſerable ſtill; if <hi>ſin</hi> (the <hi>cauſe</hi> of Wrath, as Wrath is of the Sword) <hi>lye at our doors,</hi> we are in a woful condition, though our <hi>houſes be ſafe</hi> from the fear of Enemies. But <hi>peace with God,</hi> is the foundation of abundance of Comfort in the moſt <hi>troublous</hi> times, and cauſes the <hi>ſoul to return unto its reſt,</hi> though the <hi>Ears</hi> be fill'd with the <hi>Alarms of War;</hi> for if God <hi>heal the Iniquities</hi> of a Land, we may confidently pray for the <hi>healing of its breaches,</hi> and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing regain'd his <hi>favour,</hi> we are entitled to his <hi>protection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Put away thoſe Sins,</hi> which would <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</hi> or <hi>revive</hi> the <hi>Enmity</hi> betwixt God and you. <hi>Remiſſion</hi> is beg'd and hoped for in vain, where <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> is not both reſolv'd and practis'd. All your <hi>pleadings with God</hi> will be inſignificant, while your
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47281:16"/>ſins do ſo <hi>loudly plead againſt you;</hi> their <hi>cry</hi> will be <hi>heard,</hi> and make God abſolutely <hi>deaf</hi> to yours. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain not that your <hi>Enemies are lively,</hi> while your <hi>Luſts</hi> are ſo; If you would <hi>be delivered from</hi> the one, you muſt not <hi>deliver your ſelves up to</hi> the other. So long as the <hi>Idols</hi> are <hi>ſtanding</hi> in your hearts, your <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Adverſaries</hi> are not like to be <hi>blown down</hi> by your prayers. It is a <hi>faithful ſaying,</hi> that God nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hears a ſinner for <hi>himſelf,</hi> nor for the <hi>community,</hi> which he belongs to. Sin will make both our <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications</hi> and <hi>ſwords to return empty.</hi> Therefore <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> warns the <hi>Jews,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 23.9.</note> 
                     <hi>When the hoſt goeth forth againſt thine Enemies, then keep thee from every wicked thing; i. e.</hi> then eſpecially, above all other times.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Link</hi> your pleas <hi>by Faith</hi> to the <hi>Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Jeſus Christ.</hi> Faith ought to be found in all our <hi>wreſtlings</hi> with God, and <hi>fightings</hi> with men; or elſe we ſhall onely <hi>beat the air</hi> in both. This is that which hath <hi>ſubdued Kingdoms,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.33, 34.</note> and <hi>diſperſed</hi> whole <hi>Armies of the Aliens. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> will ſpoil the good effects of our <hi>Repentance,</hi> and of all our other Duties and endeavours to pacify God, or defend our ſelves. Indeed we <hi>affront</hi> God more by <hi>diſtruſting</hi> him, than we can any other way. Now the beſt way to <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi> our Faith, and to <hi>ſecure</hi> the return of our Prayers, is to <hi>engage Chriſt</hi> as our <hi>Advocate with the Father.</hi> He is that <hi>Angel</hi> who pleaded for <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zech. 1.12.</note> at the end of the Captivity in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and whom God immediately <hi>anſwered with good and comfortable words.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zech. 1.13.</note> If the <hi>hands</hi> of this <hi>Moſes</hi> be <hi>held up</hi> in the <hi>Mount</hi> for our <hi>Engliſh Iſrael,</hi> we ſhall certainly <hi>prevail</hi> againſt the <hi>Popiſh Amalek</hi> here in the <hi>Valley.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47281:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Eye not <hi>private Revenge,</hi> nor <hi>perſonal Safety</hi> in your Requeſts, but the <hi>Glory of God.</hi> A <hi>ſingle Eye,</hi> and a pure intention in the pouring out of Prayer upon ſuch <hi>publick</hi> occaſions, is the moſt material Circumſtance.<note place="margin">Jam. 4.2, 3.</note> As men may <hi>luſt and have not,</hi> or <hi>fight and war, and yet have not,</hi> ſo they may <hi>ask and receive not, becauſe they ask amiſs.</hi> God will not work to gratifie our <hi>Malice</hi> and hatred of others, or to indulge our Love of <hi>Carnal Eaſe,</hi> but for the advancing of his <hi>own name.</hi> Let this worthy end be deſign'd by us, and God will be very ready to <hi>liſten</hi> to what we ſay, and to <hi>forward</hi> what we do: but if inſtead of being ſtirr'd up by unfeigned <hi>Zeal for God,</hi> we are tranſported with <hi>heat of Paſſion,</hi> and <hi>thirſt after Blood;</hi> we may juſtly look for a diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Temper of <hi>David,</hi> when he prayed with reſpect to his Enemies, is very imitable; <hi>ſlay them not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 59.11.</note> 
                     <hi>but ſcatter them, and bring them down, O Lord our ſheild.</hi> He did not <hi>deſire the death</hi> of theſe ſinners, but onely the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> of their power: ſo ſhould we be very well contented, though God do give our Enemies a longer <hi>ſpace of Repenting,</hi> if he cut off their further <hi>opportunities of ſinning. Self</hi> muſt not be too much concern'd in any of our Petitions; we ſhould not aim ſo much at our own reſcue from <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> as that the name of God may be lifted up above <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> and <hi>Reproach.</hi> Plead therefore for <hi>Victory</hi> with him, that you may be able to <hi>Triumph in his Praiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Be not too <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>peremptory,</hi> as to the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of Deliverance from thoſe Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whom our Hoſts do go againſt. For this is not <hi>pleading with God,</hi> but <hi>preſcribing</hi> to him. If we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47281:17"/>are <hi>ſupplicants</hi> for mercy, we ought not to be the <hi>chuſers</hi> of our own methods for receiving and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. Such things ſhould be freely left and ſubmitted to God, who is <hi>beſt able</hi> and hath <hi>moſt right</hi> to order and appoint them. To ſay, we would have Salvation juſt <hi>now,</hi> and in ſuch a <hi>way,</hi> whether God judge it expedient or no, is not to <hi>intreat</hi> with Humility, but to <hi>dictate</hi> with Confidence. If God Refuſe to joyn with ſome <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> and will have others put up in their room, we are not to murmur with <hi>impatience,</hi> but acquieſce with <hi>thankfulneſs.</hi> If God do not give in the Victory at the <hi>firſt Aſſault,</hi> but will make us <hi>wait</hi> for it, and hold out our expectations, till we are almoſt <hi>aſhamed,</hi> we ſhould be ſatisfied, and look upon the Divine will as the fitteſt rule and <hi>meaſure</hi> of our own. <hi>Particular Events</hi> perhaps many times may not be anſwerable to our deſires, but yet the <hi>final iſſue</hi> may.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.30.</note> 
                     <hi>By Faith</hi> (ſays the <hi>Apostle</hi>) <hi>the walls of Jericho fell down, after they were compaſſed about ſeven dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, Do not <hi>forfeit</hi> the benefit of Aſſiſtance and <hi>ſuccor from God,</hi> by ſinful <hi>trusting in man.</hi> There is a vaſt difference between <hi>making uſe</hi> of <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Navies,</hi> and placing our <hi>confidence</hi> in them. <hi>Ships</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> muſt not be made our <hi>Gods;</hi> for this will provoke the <hi>true God</hi> to leave us to <hi>them,</hi> and withdraw <hi>himſelf;</hi> and, whoever they are that unite with us, or ſtand up for us, it may be truly ſaid, <hi>Wo unto us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.12.</note> 
                     <hi>if he departs from us.</hi> When we make Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the <hi>Objects</hi> of our <hi>Faith,</hi> they become the <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> of our <hi>Miſery;</hi> and when we ſet them up as the <hi>Pillars</hi> of our <hi>Hope,</hi> they are turned into the <hi>Means</hi> of our <hi>ruine.</hi> It is the wretched folly of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47281:17"/>Mankind, that they know not how to keep Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their <hi>due place;</hi> they cannot <hi>employ</hi> them, without <hi>depending</hi> on them.<note place="margin">Iſa. 31.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Wo to them</hi> (ſays God) <hi>that ſtay on horſes, and truſt in horſemen, but look not to the Holy one of Iſrael, neither ſeek the Lord;</hi> perhaps they <hi>ſeek</hi> him <hi>in appearance,</hi> while they are obſerving ſuch days as theſe, but <hi>indeed</hi> they onely <hi>mock</hi> him; their applications to God are only a <hi>formality,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>ſolely expect</hi> their deliverance from other hands. So commonly do we loſe the advantage of the <hi>Arm of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>break</hi> or <hi>wither</hi> our <hi>Arms of fleſh,</hi> by <hi>leaning</hi> too much upon them. The oftner we have committed this <hi>error</hi> heretofore, the more let us beware of it now.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="question">
                  <head>Quest. II.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Queſtion which I propoſed to anſwer, (and cloſe this ſubject with) is, what <hi>encouragements have we</hi> to hope, that God may <hi>go forth with our hoſts,</hi> and <hi>bring us into the ſtrong Cities</hi> of our Enemies, upon our taking of ſuch a courſe, as hath been before di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected? I ſhall mention three things to this purpoſe, and Conclude.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>firſt ground of hope</hi> which we have, is this, that the <hi>people</hi> are God's, for whom this <hi>War</hi> is undertaken; the <hi>body</hi> of them are his by <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> and many (I doubt not) among them are his in <hi>reality.</hi> Our <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> cannot ſay ſo much; for they are not of the <hi>Church of God,</hi> but of the <hi>Synagogue of Satan;</hi> as they themſelves are bad, ſo their very profeſſion is <hi>Anti-Christian.</hi> We may take with us the words of the <hi>Jews</hi> in reference to <hi>their</hi> Enemies, <hi>we are thine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 63.19.</note> 
                     <hi>thou never bareſt rule over them.</hi> They have put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47281:18"/>under another <hi>head,</hi> who <hi>exalteth himſelf above all that is called God;</hi> they <hi>make mention of the names,</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and not of <hi>Gods only.</hi> They are the open Enemies of the <hi>true Faith</hi> of Chriſt, while we are (at leaſt) the <hi>viſible Aſſerters</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of it. Hence we can plead a <hi>relation</hi> to God, which they cannot, and we have large experience of His <hi>Affection</hi> to us, beyond moſt people in the World. There are many things which confirm this truth, that <hi>the Lord loveth our Nation;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may hope, that he will <hi>deliver us, becauſe he delights in us;</hi> ſo that theſe Kingdoms which have been <hi>his reſt ſo long,</hi> may be his reſt <hi>for ever.</hi> This is <hi>David</hi>'s argument in this very <hi>Pſalm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">ver. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>That thy belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may be delivered,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The <hi>ſecond</hi> thing which we may take ſome comfort in, is that the <hi>Cauſe</hi> is God's. It is not like the <hi>unjust</hi> and uſual <hi>Quarrels</hi> among <hi>Neighbouring Princes,</hi> where great <hi>injuries</hi> are oftentimes falſly <hi>pretended,</hi> but the enlarging of their <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> is cheifly <hi>aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at,</hi> and in order to it, the Lives of their <hi>innocent Subjects</hi> are ſacrificed by heaps. Here we may juſtly ſay, that the <hi>Honour of God</hi> and the <hi>welfare of his Church,</hi> beſides other leſſer matters of <hi>common Equity,</hi> are concern'd; and for this reaſon we may the better expect, that the <hi>Battle</hi> will be <hi>the Lords,</hi> and that he will manage it to his own glory, and our advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. The <hi>bloody Tyrant</hi> againſt whom this <hi>War</hi> is <hi>declared,</hi> and our <hi>Arms</hi> are <hi>levelled,</hi> hath made it his buſineſs and ſcope for many years upon that <hi>Throne of iniquity</hi> where he ſits, to <hi>blot out the name</hi> of a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church from under Heaven;</hi> and therefore God
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47281:18"/>(whoſe work it is to protect and vindicate the Church <hi>from</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> her great Oppreſſors) muſt needs be intereſted in this affair.<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.13.</note> 
                     <hi>He ordaineth his arrows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſecutors.</hi> Surely then <hi>ſo great a perſecutor</hi> as that <hi>Nimrod</hi> hath been, ſhould receive the <hi>largest portion</hi> in God's <hi>Quiver.</hi> While <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> (together with <hi>others</hi>) are provok't by his moſt <hi>barbarous violences</hi> to pour out their <hi>Vials</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved wrath upon him, we then may alſo hope, that at the ſame time <hi>Heaven</hi> will inflict the <hi>vengeance of the Temple.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The <hi>third</hi> and laſt thing (which I ſhall hint) from whence we may gather ſome encouragement, is this, that the <hi>work already begun,</hi> is God's. What the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> ſays, is applicable to this time,<note place="margin">Zech. 2.13.</note> the <hi>Lord is raiſed up out of his Holy habitation.</hi> The <hi>great things</hi> which he <hi>hath done for us,</hi> may embolden us to believe, that (as <hi>Chriſt</hi> told <hi>Nathaniel</hi>) we <hi>ſhall ſee greater things then theſe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 1.50.</note> and that this is but a <hi>day of ſmall things</hi> in compariſon of what we have yet to come, (unleſs our wretched folly and <hi>ingratitude</hi> prevent.) I would hope, that in our <hi>late Deliverance</hi> God laid the <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of a glorious <hi>structure,</hi> and that our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (who perhaps yet think to <hi>cauſe the work to ceaſe</hi>) ſhall never be under any temptation to ſay, <hi>he began to build, but was not able to finiſh.</hi> When God ſaved us a <hi>few months</hi> ſince,<note place="margin">Revel. 11.11, 12.</note> we were (like the <hi>riſing Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi>) ſet <hi>upon our feet;</hi> but there is a <hi>voice</hi> of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to follow, which will <hi>call us up to heaven, i. e.</hi> into a more <hi>triumphant ſtate,</hi> though upon <hi>Earth</hi> ſtill. It is not very probable, that he who excites us ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to the <hi>perfecting of holineſs,</hi> will deſiſt himſelf from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47281:19"/>the <hi>perfecting of Mercy.</hi> Though <hi>our goodneſs</hi> too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is like the <hi>morning Cloud,</hi> which ſcatters a few drops (it may be) and rowls away, yet God's it not ſo; therefore as he <hi>rested not</hi> till he had compleated the whole <hi>Host of Creatures</hi> at the firſt, ſo now we may have ſome comfortable expectation of his going on, till he hath fully reſtored the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity</hi> of his people. He that hath hitherto ſo remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably <hi>prevented</hi> our <hi>deſtruction,</hi> is the ſame God, whom we at this day ſeek unto for the <hi>working out</hi> of our <hi>Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <head type="sub">Books Printed for <hi>John Salusbury.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Period of Humane Life, determined by the Divine Will, by <hi>T. Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mighty Wonders of a Merciful Providence, in a Sermon Preached on <hi>January</hi> the 31th. 1688. Being the day of publick Thankſgiving to God for the great Deliverance of this Kingdom, by His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by <hi>T. Cruſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Uſefulneſs of Spiritual Wiſdom with a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inheritance. By the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>A Rational Defence of Non-Conformity, wherein the practice of Non-Conformiſts is vindicated from promoting Popery, and Ruining the Church, by Dr. <hi>Rule.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
